Inventory of the National Rosenberg Defence Committee records
Hoover Institution Archives
National Rosenberg Defence Committee records
1952-1954
2007C10
National Rosenberg Defence Committee (Great Britain)
2 manuscript boxes (0.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Minutes, correspondence, press releases, circulated material, pamphlets, clippings, and a photograph relating to the espionage trial and execution of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
The National Rosenberg Defence Committee was an organization created in England, most likely during 1952, as a result of the publicity surrounding the trial of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg. Maintaining contact with the New York based Committee to Secure Justice in the Rosenberg Case, this organization sought to enlist the support of the British public in the drive to obtain clemency for the Rosenbergs. Members of the committee included Felicity Whittaker, Percy Belcher, Rev. Stanley Evans, and D.N. Pritt, QC. In addition to writing letters to the editors of various leftist, union, and Jewish publications around Britain, they sought public support through sponsoring rallies in London, letter writing campaigns targeted at U.S. leaders, and other forms of protest. In one such letter writing campaign, they enlisted the support of many well-known British authors, including Graham Greene, Dylan Thomas, Sean O?Casey, and a host of others.
Following the execution of the Rosenbergs, the National Rosenberg Defence Committee sponsored a new fund to benefit their two sons. The group organized a meeting the following month to serve as a fundraiser for this new undertaking, and the following year, on the one-year anniversary of the execution of the Rosenbergs, they held another commemorative meeting in London.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains minutes, correspondence, press releases, circulated material, pamphlets, clippings, and a photograph, relating to the espionage trial and execution of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Rosenberg, Julius, 1918-1953.; Rosenberg, Ethel, 1915-1953.; Espionage, Russian -- United States.; Civil rights -- Great Britain.
Collection Contents
- Committee meeting minutes and reports, 1953-1954 (Folder 1: 1-2)
- Correspondence, 1952-1953
  - Members (Percy Belcher and Felicity Whittaker), 1952-1953 (Folder 1: 3)
  - Press, 1952-1953 (Folder 1: 4)
- Cultural material, 1952-1953 (Folder 1: 5)
  Poems, plays, essays, and songs on the Rosenberg case by Rewi Alley, Edward Eliscu, John Hutton, Ethel Rosenberg, Jean-Paul Sartre, and Edith Segal
- International counter-trial materials, 1953 April-July (Folder 1: 6)
- Letters of protest, 1952 November-1953 June (Folder 1: 7-8)
- Michael and Robert Rosenberg Fund correspondence, 1953 June-August (Folder 1: 9)
- Press releases, 1952 November-1953 June (Folder 1: 10)
- Printed material, 1952-1953
  - Circular letters and leaflets (Folder 1: 11)
  - Julius Rosenberg will and Ethel Rosenberg letter (Folder 1: 12)
  - Pamphlet typescript, notes, and design (Folder 1: 13)
    Includes small painting of Julius and Ethel Rosenberg
  - Writings by Julius and Ethel Rosenberg
- Public meetings, 1952-1954 (Folder 1: 15)
  In chronological order
  - General, 1952-1953 (Folder 1: 15)
    Includes leaflets and meeting minutes
  - St. Pancras Town Hall meeting correspondence and minutes, 1953 July (Folder 1: 16)
  - Commemoration meeting, 1954 May-June
    - Fundraising (Folder 1: 17)
    - Messages (Folder 1: 18)
    - Musical program (Folder 1: 19)
    - Platform representatives correspondence (Folder 1: 20)
    - Program and tickets (Folder 1: 21)
    - Publicity (Folder 1: 22)
    - Speakers (Folder 1: 23)
    - Venue (Folder 1: 24)
- Reference material, 1952-1954
  - General, 1952-1954 (Folder 2: 1)
    Includes photograph of the Rosenbergs' graves
  - Notes on the case, 1952-1954 (Folder 2: 2)
  - National Guardian clippings and pamphlets, 1953 (Folder 2: 3)
  - National Labor Committee for Clemency for the Rosenbergs, 1953 (Folder 2: 4)
  - News clippings, 1953 (Folder 2: 5)
  - Toronto Committee to Secure Clemency, 1953 (Folder 2: 6)
- United States Committee to Secure Justice in the Rosenberg Case, 1952-1953
  - Correspondence, 1952-1953 (Folder 2: 7)
  - Press releases, 1952 June-1953 October (Folder 2: 8-12)
  - Printed material, 1952-1953 (Folder 2: 13)